

#### RESEARCHER

Norwegian Institute for Nature Research

🛘 ~ | 🌌 Matthew.Grainger@nina.no | 🍪 uncertainecologist.netlify.com | 🖸 DrMattG | 💆 Ed\_pheasant

Wildlife, Uncertainty, Evidence synthesis, Decision models

### About me

I am an ecologist, with research interests in how we use knowledge to better inform decision making in species conservation (i.e. "Evidence-based decision making"). I develop opensource tools (in R and Shiny) that help people gather information robustly in a transparent way, interact with that information and make inference from it.

I am currently working on several projects that are fundamentally about how we make open research approaches (i.e. sharing data, sharing code, sharing best practice) as an integrated part of the workflow for biodiversity researchers and how we can take this open research and use it to help decision-makers find optimal solutions.

### **Education and qualifications**

#### **Newcastle University**

BSc (Hons) in Zoology

1994 - 1997 South Africa

UK

#### **University of Pretoria**

 ${\sf MSc\ in\ Conservation\ \&\ Planning}$ 

**University of Pretoria** 

2004 - 2005 South Africa

PHD ZOOLOGY

2008 - 2012

# **Employment history**

2021-	Researcher, NINA, Trondheim, Norway
2019-2021	Postdoctoral Fellow, NINA, Trondheim, Norway
2014-2019	Postdoctoral Research Associate, Newcastle University, UK
2013-2014	Postdoctoral Research Associate-Research Impact, Newcastle University, UK
2011-2012	Conservation Research and Support Officer, World Pheasant Ass., Newcastle, UK
2005-2006	Research Co-ordinator, Frontier-Tanzania, Tanzania

# **Rpackages**

- 1. Haddaway, N., Grainger, M., & Gray, C. (2021). Citationchaser: Perform forward and backwards chasing in evidence syntheses.
- 2. Haddaway, N., Feierman, A., Grainger, M., Gray, C., Tanriver-Ayder, E., Dhaubanjar, S., & Westgate, M. (2019). *Visualisation and mapping for datasets from systematic reviews and maps*.
- 3. Gray, C., Grainger, M., & Haddaway, N. (2021). Sysrevdata: Methods for designing multifunctional, machine readable systematic review and map databases.

# Rpackages in development\_

- 1. Haddaway, N., Grainger, M., & Gray, C. (2021). *Citationchaser: Perform forward and backwards chasing in evidence syntheses*.
- 2. Haddaway, N., Feierman, A., Grainger, M., Gray, C., Tanriver-Ayder, E., Dhaubanjar, S., & Westgate, M. (2019). *Visualisation and mapping for datasets from systematic reviews and maps*.
- 3. Gray, C., Grainger, M., & Haddaway, N. (2021). Sysrevdata: Methods for designing multifunctional, machine readable systematic review and map databases.

## **Publications**

NOVEL TOOLS AND METHODS FOR DESIGNING AND WRANGLING MULTIFUNCTIONAL. MACHINE-READABLE EVIDENCE SYNTHESIS DATABASES

2021

G Gupta, M Grainger, JC Dunn, R Sanderson, PJK McGowan

WHAT IS THE EVIDENCE AVAILABLE TO SUPPORT OUR KNOWLEDGE ABOUT THREATS TO THE CONSERVATION OF GALLIFORMES IN THE GREATER HIMALAYA?

bioRxiv 2021

H Downey, T Amano, M Cadotte, CN Cook, SJ Cooke, NR Haddaway, ...

TRAINING FUTURE GENERATIONS TO DELIVER EVIDENCE-BASED CONSERVATION AND ECOSYSTEM MANAGEMENT

Nature ecology & evolution

MJ Grainger, FC Bolam, GB Stewart, EB Nilsen

2020

Ecological Solutions and Evidence

EVIDENCE SYNTHESIS FOR TACKLING RESEARCH WASTE

B Cretois, JDC Linnell, M Grainger, EB Nilsen, JK Rød Global Ecology and Conservation

HUNTERS AS CITIZEN SCIENTISTS: CONTRIBUTIONS TO BIODIVERSITY MONITORING IN EUROPE

Measuring Business Excellence

L Aramyan, M Grainger, K Logatcheva, S Piras, M Setti, G Stewart, ... FOOD WASTE REDUCTION IN SUPPLY CHAINS THROUGH INNOVATIONS: A REVIEW

W Phumanee, R Steinmetz, R Phoonjampa, T Bejraburnin, M Grainger, ...

Ecosphere

OCCUPANCY-BASED MONITORING OF UNGULATE PREY SPECIES IN THAILAND INDICATES POPULATION STABILITY, BUT LIMITED RECOVERY

2020

TNE Gray, MJ Grainger, R Grosu

ESTIMATION

Conservation Science and Practice

Routledge Handbook of Food Waste

CONSERVATION DECISION-MAKING UNDER UNCERTAINTY: IDENTIFYING WHEN TO REINTRODUCE TIGER PANTHERA TIGRIS TO

2020

C Kandemir, C Reynolds, M Verma, M Grainger, G Stewart, S Righi, ...

DISCRETE EVENT SIMULATION; MACHINE LEARNING; BAYESIAN NETWORKS; AGENT-BASED MODELLING; AND MASS BALANCE

2020 bioRxiv

2019

M Crane, I Silva, MJ Grainger, GA Gale

ON A WING AND A PRAYER: LIMITATIONS AND GAPS IN GLOBAL BAT WING MORPHOLOGY TRAIT DATA

2020 Biological Reviews

FC Bolam, MJ Grainger, KL Mengersen, GB Stewart, WJ Sutherland, ...

J Carrick, MSAB Abdul Rahim, C Adjei, HHH Ashraa Kalee, SJ Banks, ...

2019

USING THE VALUE OF INFORMATION TO IMPROVE CONSERVATION DECISION MAKING

Journal of Flood Risk Management

IS PLANTING TREES THE SOLUTION TO REDUCING FLOOD RISKS?

NR Haddaway, A Feierman, MJ Grainger, CT Gray, E Tanriver-Ayder, ...

Environmental evidence

EVIÁTLAS: A TOOL FOR VISUALISING EVIDENCE SYNTHESIS DATABASES

2019

B Freeman, D Jiménez-García, B Barca, M Grainger

Avian Research

USING REMOTELY SENSED AND CLIMATE DATA TO PREDICT THE CURRENT AND POTENTIAL FUTURE GEOGRAPHIC DISTRIBUTION

OF A BIRD AT MULTIPLE SCALES: THE CASE OF AGELASTES MELEAGRIDES. A ...

MJ Whittingham, AJ McKenzie, RM Francksen, D Feige, T Cadwallender, ...

OFFSHORE REFUGES SUPPORT HIGHER DENSITIES AND SHOW SLOWER POPULATION DECLINES OF WINTERING RUDDY

Bird Study 2019

TURNSTONES ARENARIA INTERPRES

M Grainger, S Piras, S Righi, M Setti, G Stewart, M Vittuari

Refresh

INTEGRATED MODEL OF CONSUMER BEHAVIOURS IN RELATION TO FOOD WASTE: BEHAVIOURAL ECONOMICS: D4. 4 LINKING

2019

BAYESIAN AND AGENT-BASED MODELS TO ASSESS CONSUMER FOOD WASTE

M Grainger, EB Nilsen

NEED FOR TRANSPARENT AND REPEATABLE CONSERVATION FRAMEWORKS: REPLY TO CHILD ET AL. 2019

2019

N SUKUMAL, MJ GRAINGER, T SAVINI

Bird Conservation International

LOWER LEVELS OF HUMAN DISTURBANCE CORRESPOND WITH LONGER-TERM PERSISTENCE OF ENDANGERED GREEN PEAFOWL

2019

Nature Sustainability

PAVO MUTICUS POPULATIONS

PJK McGowan, GB Stewart, G Long, MJ Grainger

2018

AN IMPERFECT VISION OF INDIVISIBILITY IN THE SUSTAINABLE DEVELOPMENT GOALS MJ Grainger, L Aramyan, S Piras, TE Quested, S Righi, M Setti, M Vittuari, ...

PloS one

MODEL SELECTION AND AVERAGING IN THE ASSESSMENT OF THE DRIVERS OF HOUSEHOLD FOOD WASTE TO REDUCE THE

2018

2018

PROBABILITY OF FALSE POSITIVES

H Kendall, G Kaptan, G Stewart, M Grainger, S Kuznesof, P Naughton, ...

Food Control

DRIVERS OF EXISTING AND EMERGING FOOD SAFETY RISKS: EXPERT OPINION REGARDING MULTIPLE IMPACTS

Global food security

MJ Grainger, L Aramyan, K Logatcheva, S Piras, S Righi, M Setti, ...

THE USE OF SYSTEMS MODELS TO IDENTIFY FOOD WASTE DRIVERS MJ Grainger, PJ Garson, SJ Browne, PJK McGowan, T Savini

Biological conservation

CONSERVATION STATUS OF PHASIANIDAE IN SOUTHEAST ASIA

2018

F Stephenson, AC Mill, CL Scott, GB Stewart, MJ Grainger, NVC Polunin, ...

Marine Policy

SOCIO-ECONOMIC, TECHNOLOGICAL AND ENVIRONMENTAL DRIVERS OF SPATIO-TEMPORAL CHANGES IN FISHING PRESSURE

2018

S Thunhikorn, MJ Grainger, PJK McGowan, T Savini	Avian Researci
SPATIAL DISTRIBUTION OF DISPLAY SITES OF GREY PEACOCK-PHEASANT IN RELATION TO MICRO-HABITAT AND PREDATORS	201
DURING THE BREEDING SEASON  M. Grainger, D. Ngonyasert, D. McGowan, T. Savini	
M Grainger, D Ngoprasert, P McGowan, T Savini  Informing decisions on an extremely data poor species facing imminent extinction	<b>Ory</b> . 201
	Resources, Conservation and
MJ Grainger, GB Stewart	Recycling
The Jury is still out on social media as a tool for reducing food waste a response to Young et al.(2017)  LH Aramyan, MJ Grainger, K Logatcheva, S Piras, S Righi, M Setti,	201 The
FOOD WASTE REDUCTION IN SUPPLY CHAINS THROUGH INNOVATIONS: WHAT FACTORS AFFECT THE DECISION TO ADOPT	201
INNOVATIONS	REFRESI
M Grainger, G Stewart, S Piras, S Righi, M Setti, M Vittuari, LH Aramyan  D4. 3-Model Integration: Integrated Socio-economic model on Food waste	REFRESI 201
M Grainger, G Stewart, S Piras, S Righi, M Setti, M Vittuari, LH Aramyan	REFRESI
D4. 2-MODEL DEVELOPMENT AND DATA PROTOCOL	201
S Thunhikorn, MJ Grainger, PJK McGowan, T Savini	RAFFLES BULLETIN OF ZOOLOG
Assessing the population of grey peacock-pheasant (Polyplectron bicalcaratum) in a Southeast Asian	201
CONSERVATION LANDSCAPE S Thunhikorn, MJ Grainger, PJK McGowan, T Savini	Forkta
METHODS USED TO SURVEY AVIAN SPECIES AND THEIR POTENTIAL FOR SURVEYING GROUND-DWELLING BIRDS IN ASIA	201
S Thunhikorn, M Grainger, P McGowan	Newcastle Universit
A REVIEW OF METHODS USED TO SURVEY AVIAN SPECIES AND THEIR POTENTIAL FOR SURVEYING GROUND-DWELLING BIRDS IN	201
ASIA	
S Thunhikorn, MJ Grainger, PJK McGowan, T Savini  Assessing the population status of Grey Peacock-pheasant (Polyplectron bicalcaratum) in Huai Kha Khaeng, a	Raffles Bulletin of Zoolog
ASSESSING THE POPULATION STATUS OF GREY PEACOCK-PHEASANT (POLYPLECTRON BICALCARATUM) IN HUAI KHA KHAENG, A KEY CONSERVATION LANDSCAPE IN SOUTHEAST ASIA	201
	Occasional paper of the IUC
DP Mallon, M Hoffmann, MJ Grainger, F Hibert, N Van Vliet,	species survival commissio
An IUCN situation analysis of terrestrial and freshwater fauna in West and Central Africa <b>FHA Aalen, MJ Grainger, F Hibert, M Hoffmann, DP Mallon,</b>	201 IUC
Analyse de situation de l'UICN concernant la faune terrestre et d'eau douce en Afrique centrale et de l'Ouest <b>M Grainger, R van Aarde</b>	201 Ecological Restoratio
Can Non-Native Species Explain Patterns of Convergence and Deviation in Regenerating Coastal Dune Forest?  MJ Grainger, RJ Van Aarde	201 African Journal of Ecolog
The role of canopy gaps in the regeneration of coastal dune forest	201
M Grainger, P McGowan, A McKenzie, J Minderman, JP Rodriguez,  METHOD FOR THE ASSESSMENT OF PRIORITIES FOR INTERNATIONAL SPECIES CONSERVATION (MAPISCO)	201
MJ Grainger, RJ Van Aarde	Ecological Restoratio
IS SUCCESSION-BASED MANAGEMENT OF COASTAL DUNE FOREST RESTORATION VALID?	203
PJK McGowan, LL Owens, MJ Grainger	Animal Biodiversity an Conservatio
GALLIFORMES SCIENCE AND SPECIES EXTINCTIONS: WHAT WE KNOW AND WHAT WE NEED TO KNOW  RAR Guldemond, MJ Grainger, MJ Trimble	201 Restoration Ecolog
Where is the Evidence for Assessing Evidence-Based Restoration? Comments on Ntshotsho et al.(2010)  MJ Grainger, RJ van Aarde, TD Wassenaar	201 Restoration Ecolog
Landscape composition influences the restoration of subtropical coastal dune forest  MJ Grainger	201 University of Pretori
An evaluation of coastal dune forest restoration in northern KwaZulu-Natal, South Africa  MJ Grainger, RJ Van Aarde	201 Wiley-Blackwe
RESILIENCE OF THE MEDICINAL PLANT COMMUNITY OF REHABILITATING COASTAL DUNE FORESTS, KWAZULU-NATAL, SOUTH	200
AFRICA C Bonnington, M Grainger, S Dangerfield, E Fanning	African Journal of Ecolog
The influence of electric fences on large mammal movements in the Kilombero Valley, Tanzania	Airicuit Journal of Ecolog
C Bonnington, MD Steer, J Lamontagne-Godwin, N Owen, M Grainger  EVIDENCE FOR LOCAL DECLINES IN TANZANIA'S PUKU ANTELOPE (KOBUS VARDONI LIVINGSTONE, 1857) POPULATION BETWEEN	African Journal of Ecolog
EVIDENCE FOR LOCAL DECLINES IN TANZANIA'S PUKU ANTELOPE (KOBUS VARDONI LIVINGSTONE, 1857) POPULATION BETWEEN 1999 AND 2003	203
1272 MINU (1002)	

LANDSCAPE HETEROGENEITY AND THE USE OF SPACE BY ELEPHANTS IN THE KRUGER NATIONAL PARK, SOUTH AFRICA

African Journal of Ecology

2005

M Grainger, R Van Aarde, I Whyte